- [Louis] There's so much kinda
of trans stuff going on now,
but it tends to all be white, you know?
and I don't really wanna
kind of support the idea
that all trans folks, or all transsexuals
are all European-Americans.
- [Kylar] You know, we have gay TV now.
I was just watching it the other day
and they have tons of trans people,
it's like, but none of color, any color.
So I just think it's important
that we get our stories told
and our voices heard.
- [Nicholas] I hope that this film
just really just get out there to where
it wouldn't be a question
like, or someone said,
"I never heard of a trans guy before."
To where it'll just
be, "Oh yeah, you know,
"he a T guy or whatever,"
and put it on top that he's Black
You know.
It's like, wow.
(jazzy music)
- As a kid, I always
used to play Perry Mason.
I was weird kid, you know,
other people wanted to
play dolls or whatever.
I wanted to play Perry Mason.
So I would, and every Saturday,
after watching the
episodes of Perry Mason,
my bed, and my room
would be my little table
and I would, you know, do cases.
And so, and I mean, I probably
was four or five then.
So, and then I did that and
I really just loved that.
And then as I grew, this
activism part of me grew,
but it was because my parents
were very active in the community.
For them, their activism was
through the American Legion,
because my parents, my father
was a World War II veteran,
my mother 10 years younger than he,
and they've been lifelong sweethearts.
And since she was 14, through
their whole lives together,
so, but they were very
active in the community,
through the American
Legion, through the church,
you know, Second Baptist Church.
And so I saw that and went with them
to clean the graveyards, to
mow other people's lawns,
to do these things, and
also just their attitudes
of you stand up for what you believe in.
And both my parents were stand up
for what you believe in people,
that, that just propelled my advocacy.
And when my life unfolded,
it was so important to fight
for rights of just
human beings in general.
And, and of course that
is my love and my passion.
I worked in corporate
America and went to work
in corporate America after law school,
again, thinking I'm not
going to be the cliche,
the black civil rights lawyer,
the black lesbian at the time,
'cause that was the title that I thought
was closest to who I was at the time.
And so, I went to work
in this corporation,
gonna make lots of money.
So I was going to conform.
It was horrible because
then I had to dress
or try to dress like they
wanted with hose and makeup.
And I don't know any people
that wear those things,
but it's quite costly
to buy makeup and hose
and all those things, and
then you have to get up
at the crack of dawn to get dressed.
(audience laughing)
So you can tell, I'm kinda poor at that,
which is why my head is shaved.
I've never been for getting up early, but,
(audience laughing)
but at any rate.
I would just rip those clothes off,
as soon as I got in the
car, out of the work,
in the parking lot, you
know, and I couldn't stand,
you know, just as soon
as I could get them off.
I mean, I'd just be undressing as soon
as I got to the parking lot,
'cause it was just horrible
and the makeup, the thought of makeup,
and then I tried to use
as little as possible.
And luckily, my skin is sensitive,
so I could use that as an excuse
to not wear makeup or what they expected.
And those dress codes held through,
really for most women into the '90s.
And in some places, depending
upon where you live,
that's still a fight.
And so my girlfriend, every
day we'd get up and say,
okay, this is a uniform, to
get me dressed every day.
I mean, it was really a
psychological, it's like,
okay, okay, and I mean,
I would put the stuff on
and I would be so uncomfortable
carrying the purse around.
I'll never forget that.
I had a good buddy that I worked with,
and he would remember the purse
because I had never remembered the purse.
And he's like, God, you carry
that like a lunch bucket
and blah, blah, blah, blah.
And I'm like, dude, you know, whatever.
So I gave up the purse part,
but he said to me, when I
stopped trying to do that,
"Thank God you stopped doing that.
"You looked horrible."
And I said to him, "You're my,"
at the time, "very good friend.
"Why didn't you tell me?
"I expect my friends to tell
me the truth," and he says,
you know, he didn't want
to hurt my feelings.
It's just like, well, next
time, tell me the truth.
And I did, I looked horrible.
And I liked to say, I looked
like a bad drag queen, and I did, so.
And I don't think I was fooling anybody
but myself because who I
was transcended the clothes.
And eventually I got a new
boss who'd made my life hell
and I was outta there
after announcing transition
in six months, six months,
it was like fast, boom.
And I had been a good employee.
I just didn't think that
company would ever do that.
Just Pollyanna, I did a good job.
Why would they wanna get rid of me?
Because we know that how you get promoted
is how you look, right?
How we get elected or how we
do anything is how we look.
So if we're treated differently,
and I can always analogize
this part of me to race,
where a lot of times
we're treated differently
because we were a certain race,
that really ostracizes us,
it doesn't really help or benefit us
in any realm of the imagination
and makes matters worse.
That's the whole dress thing
that I got on at Harvard,
because I'm really passionate about that,
about people feeling
like they can go to work
and be comfortable, and
not have an expectation
of having to be a certain
way or to be forced
to be feminized or, or
gendered or whatever.
I started doing a lot of trans conferences
because I wanted to get legal information
out there about name changes,
document changes, and so forth.
And people weren't doing that then.
And the big organization,
nobody was doing that then.
And me, and I would
meet a couple other guys
doing the trans circuit, so to speak,
and we'd go to conferences and doing that.
And that kinda started my
advocacy in the trans community,
just doing those Trans 101s
of how you get your documents,
where you get your documents,
and how to navigate the process.
And that helped me come into, you know,
because then that allowed me to connect
to other trans people
and then to learn more
about myself and embrace myself.
And one of the best things
were going to the conferences,
And I remember True Spirit Conference
when it was just like a few of us,
then a grew to larger and larger
and a lot more trans people,
but just being able to go there
and have somebody understand, you know,
even without saying
what your experience is
and just going, wow, look at
you, look at you, look at you.
You know, it's like,
wow, you're buff there,
you're this you're that, you know,
all these things are happening.
What are you doing about
scars on your chest?
You know, is my surgery comparable?
Not meaning, you know, we're one ups man,
but did I get a good job or not?
Does it look real and
showing each other our chest,
you know, talking about
issues, how do you date?
You know, how do you dress?
And then it was nice
doing ones with the MTFs,
because they would like
exchange clothes with us
to help with teaching
guys how to tie ties.
And I think that was really a
part of my growing experience
is going to the trans
conferences and connecting
with other people, and
now they've grown up
to such much, more advocacy,
much more politically astute conferences,
which is a good thing.
But the beginning ones, when
it was just a few people
coming together, were
some of the best ones.
When I first started my activism,
I talked a lot about race and just being,
you know, gay, lesbian,
bisexual, transgender.
And when, particularly, when I would go
to transgender conferences,
'cause I didn't want us to do
what the gay movement had done,
but we do, we're doing it,
exactly the same thing,
'cause we are part of that
and have become part of
that whole hierarchy.
And you see it in the
movement, they will hire,
and I got in trouble with saying
this in corporate America,
but they will hire a white person
over a qualified black person
and think nothing of it.
And they're, well, where can
we find qualified black people?
Where are they at?
Where are qualified Hispanic
people, Asian people,
when we're there, we're
there at the table,
we're visible, but we're looked over.
We're never considered as qualified.
And then we don't get into
the decision making positions
in the organizations that make decisions
about the gay movement and the decisions
that are made in lobbying
for bills and legislation.
Sure, we get invited to the table,
one or two of us get invited to the table
because a few people feel like, oh,
well, we should look for parity,
but I don't feel like that's
a real concern in the,
at large movement, if
you will, that it is,
be diverse racially,
economically or otherwise,
because no oppression
is greater than another.
And I get very angry about
that when I have some people,
particularly people that are not of color,
try to call me on that because
there is a lot of energy
and anger around being
of color in this country.
And we have a right to own that.
And I had somebody say, oh,
well, one's not any greater,
well, no one isn't any
greater than the other,
but don't assume, you know my experience
until you've walked in my shoes
and don't dismiss it at all.
And I get angry because I feel
it's dismissed all the time.
And I don't mean to
personalize it just to me
because I see it happen to my brothers
and sisters within the
community as well, so.
But I think we get it from all sides.
And you know, in
employment, it's very clear,
we are not white men, so it's very clear,
that hierarchy, and I
think pay is affected.
I work for a historically black college.
So I think that's a
little bit differently,
but I think race plays a part there.
In any job environment where you interact
with people of other races and ethnicity.
I feel so marginalized a lot of times
by people and things and
my life experience that,
yeah, it felt like a milestone
to be asked to go to Harvard
because people usually
diss my intelligence
on a daily basis.
They do do due to my race or
because I'm a transsexual.
And so I'm discounted as a person.
It's hard for me when I practice, here,
in the city I live in, because
of the negativity of that.
And one of my clients go
to court with me one day
and he comes out, he goes,
"I don't know how you stand
that on a daily basis."
And just the, there is the hate there.
there is the how dare you?
I did a case the other day,
and I know the other attorney
left angry and crying because
a transsexual black person
beat her, you know, and
it didn't dawn on me,
'cause that's not the
first thing I wanna think.
But that's, you know,
why, 'cause she had gone
to law school with me,
she had graduated with me,
the whole elitist, you know,
even in law school things,
she was part of that
whole elitist echelon.
So how is this black person
and this transsexual person
gonna even be able to be
as intelligent as I am?
So that's where it comes from to be like,
well, you know, I get invited to Harvard
and I speak at Harvard Law School,
when most people won't
even hire me for a job
or treat me horribly when they do.
I have a whole theory around passing,
having been high yellow, and
that's what it was called
back in my day is that
I don't like passing,
which is why I do come out to people.
I'm very proud to be a black American.
I'm very proud to be who I am.
And I think that if you're
not proud to be who you are,
people can use that as power against you.
And plus why wouldn't you love yourself
or be who you are and embrace who you are?
So I think that's very
important for people to do.
And I never looked back a day.
People ask me, do you regret?
'Cause I had friends,
they worried, you know,
they're two gay guys,
every time they're like,
are you regret, do you regret?
I've never regretted one day my decision,
because it was life or
death for me at that point,
and it wouldn't be worth living
if I wasn't living who I am.
And there have been tons of hard times
and not being paid enough
and barely making ends meet
and feeling limited in job
choices because of who I am,
but I still wouldn't trade being myself.
So at all.
(upbeat music)
- My family is pretty,
well, they think that,
they say that they're liberal,
but they're pretty conservative
when it comes right down to it.
They had a really hard time,
'cause before I transitioned,
I came out as a lesbian
when I was really young
and they had a really hard time with that.
And then when I decided
that I needed to transition,
they, I don't, my father,
I haven't really talked
about transition with.
I think he knows, but we
just don't talk about it.
I remember asking my father
when I was about three years old
when my penis was gonna grow
and it totally freaked him
out, totally freaked him out.
But I knew, like I don't
know, I would see little boys
and just always wanted to be with them.
You know, always wanted to do the things
that they were doing,
always wanted to hang out
with them, you know, all the time.
And I hated having to
wear the things that,
you know, the dresses and whatnot.
And especially when you're
two and three years old,
you kinda have to wear
whatever your parents
put on you, you know?
And I would always be ripping stuff off
and wanting to go around
in just a diaper, you know,
and just couldn't understand
why I couldn't just wear,
you know, a pair of shorts
and a t-shirt, you know,
like everybody else was.
Well, one time we had to
go to a choir rehearsal
and he had this blue,
this powder blue pantsuit
that he bought for me,
he wanted me to wear it.
So I did, you know, and we went,
we got to the rehearsal
and there's this woman,
this like 60 year old woman wearing
the exact same thing that I was wearing.
And it just freaked me out.
And I was like, I got in the car.
I'm like, there's no way I'm
ever wearing this thing again.
I'm never gonna wear this again.
And so I got home and,
you know, we did laundry
and washed it and everything, and I said,
"Well, I need to iron this, you know,
"just to make sure that it looks nice
"the next time I wear it."
So I accidentally on
purpose, burned a hole in it
with the iron so that I
wouldn't have to wear it again.
And I mean, you know,
he acted like it was,
you know, I acted like
it was a big accident.
And he was like, he knew
that I didn't wanna wear it,
but he never bought anything
like that for me again.
But yeah, childhood
was interesting for me.
It was very interesting for me.
I have, I was born with cerebral palsy.
It mostly affects my legs,
but I do have some involvement
in my hands and it makes
it difficult to walk.
Before my transition,
I had like 27 surgeries
to try to straighten out my legs
and straighten out my back and all that.
So I spent a good deal of
my childhood in a hospital.
So I didn't really, I wasn't really social
in ways that other kids are.
And so I didn't, I don't,
I never really learned
how to do those, you know,
like be, make friends,
you know, in school and stuff like that.
So now I'm sort of, you know,
sort of learning those things.
There's a lot of things that I don't know
about how to interact with people as male,
because I was socialized as female.
So I kind of, I tend to defer more.
Like, I don't know.
When someone's talking to me,
if I'm talking with a woman,
I tend not to look at them as much
as I do when I'm talking to a man.
And I don't know what, I'm
not sure whether that's about,
although I don't look at men.
I mean, I do look at men like, you know,
I'm a gay man, I look at men,
but I don't really look them in the eye
as much as I would like to.
And so I feel like I'm not
being taken seriously a lot
because I can't, I have a hard time
looking people in the
eye because as a woman,
I was always taught
that you lower your eyes
when people are speaking to
you, lower your eyes a bit.
And so I'm still trying to
get used to just looking
at people full in the face, you know?
And that's been hard.
In terms of, but I think
also being a black man
is very different than
being a black woman.
And so I'm learning
sort of how to interact
with people that way.
A lot of people are afraid to approach me
because they see black
man, and they're like,
okay, what's he gonna
do to me kinda thing.
You know, and what am I, you know,
when I think about me, it's like,
what am I going to do
to anybody, you know?
I mean, I can remember last
winter getting stuck somewhere
in my power chair and wanting, you know,
looking for someone to stop and help me.
And nobody would stop.
It's like, what am I going to do?
Carjack you from my wheelchair, you know?
I mean, and all I needed
was a push out of the snow.
Finally someone stopped, and,
but they wouldn't get out of the car.
They rolled down the window and said,
do you want me to call the police?
It's like, no, if you
would just come push me,
I could get where I need to go, you know?
'Cause I was like a block from my house,
it was like, you call the police,
it's gonna take them 45
minutes to get out here,
and they're going to do
exactly the same thing,
but I'm gonna be frozen, you know?
So I don't get that.
I don't understand like how that works,
and how someone gets used to
being perceived in that way.
You know, I just don't understand it,
but I'm learning how to deal with it.
It's hard being a black
man in this society.
And I never really recognized that before,
but now that I am one, I see the,
the oppression and the
prejudice that people
have towards black men.
And it's very scary, and I
also recognize that in myself,
that I have some of that in myself
and I'm trying to change that.
I have a lot of internalized
racism and prejudice,
and I'm trying to change that.
In terms of the way that the
media portrays black men,
I have a lotta issues, a
lotta issues around that
because I know that
I'm perceived that way,
in a lot of situations, and I'm not that.
I mean, most of the time, it's either,
you either see black men being portrayed
as superstar athlete or criminal,
and there's nothing in between.
And I have a really hard time with that
because I'm not, obviously
not a superstar athlete,
but I'm also not a criminal, you know?
And the only other representation
that I've seen lately is Barack Obama,
and I'm not that, either.
So I think that it's really important
to get a different
perspective on what black men,
who black men are, you know?
It's been a long struggle
for me to figure out
what kinda man I wanna be.
And basically what I
discovered is that I'm already
the man that I wanna be,
I just have to live it.
I'm not doing this to
make my life easy or hard.
It's not, you know, it's
not a choice that I have.
It's something that I have to do,
in order to be comfortable and to live.
Who's to say, who can really say
whether this is real for you?
Who can say whether it's real for you?
Only you can say that.
No doctor's really gonna
be able to tell me that,
no, you don't have, no,
you're not a transsexual.
Well, yeah, I am, you know?
You can't tell me that I'm not, you know,
unless you live in my body, you can't,
nobody can know but me, so.
And it took a good three
years before I got my surgery,
my chest surgery done.
But it was, that was
the hardest three years
that I've ever spent.
The hysterectomy wasn't
as important to me,
although I did wanna have it
done, it wasn't as important.
'Cause you can't see that, you know?
But having breasts was just like,
this is not what a guy's
supposed to look like, you know?
'Cause I mean, I had a,
starting to get a beard,
and I had a mustache and
stuff and was looking
a lot more masculine and then,
there's these big honking,
you know, and it's just like,
ugh, no, no, can't do it.
(laughs) You know?
I think sexuality and gender
are very much separate,
and I've always been attracted
to men, but I wasn't really,
I wasn't attracted to straight men.
Like I could never imagine
myself being in that kind
of a relationship where I was
perceived as being straight,
just, I couldn't do it.
But I knew that the men
that I was attracted to,
'cause I was mostly attracted to gay men,
they wouldn't wanna be
with me in the body,
the way that my body was.
Now that I've transitioned, and so,
I figured ,I wanted to be a
part of the gay community.
So I lived as a lesbian for a long time,
just so mainly so that I can
be part of the community,
but I did fall in love with a woman.
And that was really difficult for me when,
'cause she died of cervical cancer
and it was really difficult
for me to reconcile the fact
that I know that I've
always been a gay man
with the fact that I fell
in love with this woman,
but it ended up working out
okay, in terms of, we both,
we loved each other and that's
all that matters, really.
But really, love is the only
thing that really matters
and you can't really help
who you fall in love with.
So me falling in love with this woman was,
it was disconcerting, but at
the same time, it was love.
So, you know, what are
you, how can you beat that?
But I don't think that,
I think that my sexuality
really hadn't changed, hasn't changed
because I've always been gay.
You know, I just, I was
with a woman for awhile
and now I'm I'm with men, you know,
and most of the men that I've been with
since I transitioned
were, have been trans men,
but I'm not gonna rule out the possibility
of being with a bio male, either.
'Cause that, that's like,
would be fun, you know?
'Cause it's always fun, you know?
And for me, as long as I'm
not hurting anybody else,
you know, unless they asked me to,
and I'm not doing anything that's illegal,
if it feels good, I'm gonna do it, so.
I've always wanted, I
always wanted tattoos
from the time that I was
really, really young.
And I just decided that I
was gonna do it one day.
So on my 18th birthday,
actually I went and got a tattoo
for myself and my parents
kinda freaked out about it,
you know, the whole, that whole thing.
But I figured, you know, this is like,
it's a coming of age
kind of thing, you know?
And guys do that when they
turn 18, they get tattoos.
So I'm gonna get a tattoo.
You know, I'm a guy, I'm
18, I'm gonna get a tattoo.
So that's what I did.
The piercings, that I was, (chuckling)
that I've been doing a lot longer.
I mean, I wanted to get my ears pierced
when I was real little, but my
father wouldn't let me do it
until I was like 15, and
then, once I turned 18,
it was just like, I went wild and I mean,
I had like 20 piercings in one ear
and then I got this huge plug put in,
and my eyebrows, I had
both my eyebrows pierced.
I had my lip pierced all along here.
I had my nose pierced in my septum,
and both nostrils pierced.
I had surface piercings
along my neck for a while.
It was just, and I mean, that again
is another spiritual thing,
tattoos and piercings.
They take me to another place
and it's just like a
connection with something
that's so outside of myself, you know,
I feel just euphoric when I get them done.
I absolutely love them and I will do them
until the day I die.
I know that I will always get,
whenever I have enough money,
you know, after all my
stuff, all my necessities
and all the obligations
that I have are done,
if I have any extra money,
that's where it goes.
I don't even buy books that much anymore,
and I love to read, but I don't
buy books that much anymore
because I wanna get pierced and tattooed.
You know, it's just, it's
that important to me, so.
(upbeat music)
- We ask that you'd bless
this service today, Lord.
- [Congregation] Yes.
- That you'd bless each and
every one who's here today,
Lord, there are some
here who have the hurt,
some here who have pain.
Lord, we ask that you'd mend
their hearts today, Lord.
Mend their bodies today, Lord.
Mend their spirits today, Lord,
in the name of Jesus.
We ask that the Word goes forth, Lord,
today, in the name of Jesus.
We ask that you have your glory shine
through your words today, Lord Jesus.
We ask that you bless our pastor today,
as she delivers the Word today, Lord.
We ask that you'd bless the
musicians here today, Lord.
We ask that you'd bless
our praise team, Lord,
as they sing praises to your name.
As always, Lord, we give you the praise,
to you, the honor and the glory.
In your Son, Jesus' name, we pray.
- Worthy!
- Amen.
- [Congregation] Amen.
(congregation cheering)
(congregation applauding)
- I've had this calling for a long time.
I'm just one of those who,
who's fighting the call,
'cause like I say, I'm a
behind the scenes person
and now, God is trying to push me forward.
And I'm like, I don't, you know, but I,
I do what I'm supposed to do,
but I'm doing it begrudgingly.
We live our name.
When we say we were a pillar of love
'cause people always say
that they, they feel a love
when we come through, when
they come through the doors
and it's genuine.
There's people who've called
the church, a pillar of hope
a pillar of life, and I
tell them, you know what?
Don't even worry about
that because folks there,
that's what you're feeling.
You're feeling that
you've come to this church
and folks are coming half dead.
But you come here and
you're feeling a love
and you're feeling alive again.
There's people who come,
they're looking for hope
and they find that hope and
they, and they find that love
to say, "Wow, I can be
gay, bisexual, transgender,
"and still have a relationship with God."
Whatever you identify as,
whatever your religion is,
or you don't have a religion
or your spirituality,
we welcome all, and it's a good place.
I'm glad that I'm there.
My kids have grown up in the church,
which I've always wanted.
I've never grew up in the
church, so this is new for me.
My mother always sent me to church,
but she never went to church.
I'm like, that's not right.
You know, how you gonna tell
me I need to go to church
and you're not going to church yourself?
But for all of us, my wife and my kids,
to all go as a family, it's,
it's a wonderful thing.
We met at church and she
tells me when she saw me,
she thought I was a guy,
but she thought I was a,
what did you say?
- Flaming.
- A flaming guy? (laughs)
Like why I gotta be flaming?
She thought I was a flaming guy.
And when I was preaching the one Sunday
and my mom and uncle were there,
so, you know, I said,
you know, I told them,
"My name is Deacon Carl, and
for those of you who are here,
"my family is here, knows me as Caroline."
And that's when she was
like, "Oh, you're a female."
And she was all smiles.
And afterwards, you know,
you greet everybody.
She's all smiles and was like,
"Ooh, I really enjoyed your sermon.
"And do you have any discussions
and stuff like that?"
And I'm like, well, yeah,
you know, we, you know,
we can talk or whatever like that.
A lot of back and forth with us.
We ended up finally getting
together after a year or two.
And my mother was ill.
She was diabetic and she was ill,
and she couldn't get around a lot.
And what meant a lot to me,
and I think it meant a lot
to my mother was the Christmas
before my mother passed,
Wanda took my mother
out Christmas shopping
and no one would've ever had the patience
to take my mother Christmas shopping.
And she, you know, she would
always just give me money.
And I knew it meant to her
that she would wanna
go Christmas shopping.
And Wanda took her and
nobody else would think,
well, when we get there,
put her in the wheelchair.
You know?
And that's what they did.
They went to Target.
They, she pushed in the wheelchair
and they had a good time.
And then it meant a lot to my mother,
'cause she was able to do that.
And we went to the show in January.
And for her birthday, she
loved Denzel Washington.
So we went to see Denzel Washington.
And unfortunately, then,
the following months,
she just, she passed away suddenly.
But it just, it really meant a lot to me
what Wanda did for my mother,
'cause no other woman has
ever done that for her.
And even when my mother passed,
and Wanda and I had a
falling out that weekend,
and my mother passed and I
told her I was at the hospital.
I said, "My mom died."
And she was like, "Where are you?
"Where are you," I just hung up the phone,
'cause I didn't want to talk about it.
And next thing I know, she
done popped up at the (laughs),
I was like, "How you know where I was?"
And God spoke to me and says,
"This is gonna be your wife,
"whether you like it or not,"
just like I am with my ministry,
this is going to be your wife, and we got
our domestic partnership a
year later and we decided
to have kids 'cause I'm like,
I'm getting old. I need to.
And they gave us a 0.07% chance
that we would have our
babies and, or a baby.
'Cause before, we always
talked about one baby
and lo and behold two
came, and the next thing,
I found out they were
girls, I was like, see,
I got to get another job,
'cause I got three women
in the house now.
- The pregnancy-
- Nah, it's not gonna work.
- I had successfully become pregnant.
But my, my journey-
- Tell them how.
Right, they took my eggs.
- Oh yeah, they took
his eggs fertilized it
with anonymous sperm that
we got from a sperm bank,
and then implanted them in me.
So this is when they told
us we got 0.7% chance.
Okay.
So we get up, we get past the first month.
we get past the second
month and they're like,
wow, you shouldn't be this, you know,
it should be terminated right now.
And I'm feeling all these weird pains.
And then we get to the third month,
and then we get to the fourth month,
I'm like, you know,
people, I'm really sure
that I should not be feeling these pains.
You know, everybody thought I was crazy.
And I'm like, no, I'm pretty sure
I'm not supposed to be feeling this.
Come to find out I was
in labor at four months.
Yeah.
So I had to be put on
bedrest from my fourth month,
all the way to the time I had the babies
and they had to sew me up,
giving me this thing called us a cerclage.
And that was very trying
on our relationship
because I couldn't do anything.
I had to get permission just to go
to the bathroom for myself.
So, you know, I needed around
the clock, you know, help.
And you know, our church
family came together
like you wouldn't believe,
and they all supported us
and they would come
give me meals, you know,
try to do like our dishes
and things like that
because he's used to me doing
everything and you know,
otherwise our house look
a mess all the time.
So they had to do that.
So both came out perfectly fine
through prayer and hard work.
- Definitely prayer.
- Yeah.
- Definitely.
So that, I mean that story,
it's a little bit more detailed,
but as you can see, it's priceless, yeah.
Yeah, and we want to
help other other couples.
So we were thinking about
putting a book out there
to help couples, help conceive,
and everything because why
shouldn't we be able to have
the perfect family, like everybody else,
like the heterosexuals, you know?
We don't have a white picket fence yet,
but pretty much we got everything else.
- Like I said, she's, through all my BS,
Wanda has, has been there
for me, and I don't know.
I think she crazy, but
I thank God for her,
that through all of our mess, you know,
she's been with me and
we're still together.
You know, we have our ups and our downs,
but we're trying to work things out,
and get together and do this thing
'cause we don't wanna be separated,
and we don't want our kids
to grow up in separate homes.
We want them to have
a mother and a father.
I have a little chauvinist in me
and I'm trying to get over
that and, and learning that
your woman's not supposed
to do everything,
but it's hard, and it's
funny because people say,
well, where did you get this idea?
Because your uncles are not like that.
And it's watching TV.
You know, my mother even told me,
you need a 1950s woman because you know,
you want everybody to
do this and it's true.
I wanted, you know, you
stay home with the kids.
I come home, bring home
the bacon, woo-wop, da bam.
But that's not working.
It's like no, I'm not getting
paid enough money to do this.
So I have to learn how to,
and it's a learning process,
learn how to make my wife my equal.
You know, she's not in
front of me, behind me.
She's next to me.
And it's weird that I feeling myself
being pulled towards being
an activist for women.
Actually my pastor's partner, she works
for a rape crisis hotline,
and I've been feeling myself
being pulled to, to be there,
work with her with that.
And I had actually
asked her about training
and she's like, it's an in-depth training,
but she, you know, she thinks
that it's good for that.
And because just like anybody else,
women are not treated right, either,
whether they're in a heterosexual,
homosexual relationship
and I'm starting to see
that people in my church,
and I know that a lot of
feminists in my church,
and they're letting me see
things in a different light.
And I'm like, I'm glad
that they've done that
because I didn't see it at that way.
And they show me like, you know, Carl,
this is really how you are.
You're very oppressing your partner
and you shouldn't do that.
And then it's interesting.
I see myself being an activist also.
Starting in January, I'm with this,
I'm gonna be a mentor, starting a group
with African American, young trans men
and working with two other people
and just having a little
monthly group meeting with them
and to mentor the young
guys and everything.
And I wanna teach them how
to be a good young man.
Being African-American, I wanna show
a positive side to black men.
There's so many stereotypical
things about black men
that I don't like, and I know
I'm a positive black man.
I'm married, I have kids, I work,
and I'm a minister, I go to church.
So I'm not thuggin' and a
buggin' and all this other stuff,
trying to hustle, but
you know, I'm just here
having a house, a home with my family.
And I think that's a positive thing,
but society has us as a negative.
(upbeat music)
- I wrote poetry to stay alive
and I've always written to stay alive.
I've either done that or music.
And I really got hooked
onto Saul Williams.
I saw the movie "Slam,"
and it ended it for me.
Like I was writing this cheesy ass poetry,
like the sun rises and stuff,
and I saw "Slam," and
I was like, oh my God.
And he will always be, he
will always be like my,
you know, I hate idols, but
he will always be that guy
who really pulled me out of myself.
And then "Common" came on the scene for me
and blew it out the box.
And then Tylique, I met
him actually this summer.
I mean, Mos Def, and all of these people
who I had not listened to,
because I was in this utopia
and lying to myself about my identity,
chose not to listen to,
or to be involved in.
And I, and I got into hip-hop
and I got into poetry,
and it really just
changed my world in terms
of me being comfortable
with my identity too.
So that's how I started poetry,
I wrote poetry all the time,
but it never really progressed
to the point until I was at
a breaking point in my life
where I could've lived or
died, you know, literally.
So.
(upbeat music)
Kermit thought it wasn't easy being green.
And so when his puppet
world of make believe,
he believed in teaching
children on public television
about racism, prejudice,
and how really mean the world can be.
He reached me through him melodic songs,
teaching me my ABCs,
how to respect my toys,
how not to hate boys,
and generally I received,
I received in cars, parks,
my mother's basement,
adjacent to where my childhood struggles
always rustled my sheets,
the three Rs became regret,
regression, reiterating
that it wasn't easy
being brown either.
Neither was being born into a system,
made to keep my face unseen,
wrinkles of scorn made to conform.
I sit in my mother's computer swivel chair
while she pressed my hair.
Every Sunday, my mother never
washed my hair on Monday
because Sunday was the Sabbath day.
So I'm kinda skeptical of Christianity
'cause if Jesus is really
white and heaven is forever,
will I suffer in eternity?
When I sit down here looking
up, it's His eyes down on me,
down on myself, I used to
put razor blades to my arms
as indigenous tribe markings
to keep you alarmed.
Red and black, get back Jack,
like The Scarlet Letter and
rules of the Boy Scouts,
I grew stout, that was
that, but not like the PA's,
but I will often enter the
offices with PhD markings.
Doctors couldn't find what was wrong.
Years were shorter instead of long.
And I long for the moment
you where I would wake up
like Luca with a struggle on my back.
Instead of hunching it
over, letting it roll down,
trying to keep my coloredness in the back.
And I'd often retract, taking
seats in the back of buses.
It's always warmer there.
And no matter how often people stare,
I hum a song, my ancestors' song.
♪ Swing low, sweet chariot ♪
but this bus isn't taking me home.
Underground, the mini railroads,
I found and regain this
freedom and this time
I will not follow the drinking gourd,
'cause if I consume on an
ounce of liquid, I converse,
my father's father's
father's fathers had seen
too much water in their lifetimes,
so I ignore my thirst.
I wanna go back to the time of my birth,
where I shaped my mother's
belly with psychotic telepathy,
consisting of only cells instead
of existing in this jail.
Only time will tell, but
it's already been 400 years,
428 years, and I still can't
see past my broad nose.
And I only get 28 days in
February to say it loud.
I'm black and I'm proud,
but it takes a little longer
to fake it till you make it.
Reality hit me hard.
Like Adam and Eve,
realizing they were naked.
Even before I could spell, I was writing,
even before I knew my
letters, I was writing.
It sounds so cheesy, but
you could ask my mom,
I would scribble some crap down
and be like, dah, dah, dah.
So I've always been a writer,
and that's just my passion,
that's what I wanna do.
When I get, when I got into college,
I went to go get a checkup or something.
And the doctor's like, you
know, noticed something.
And I was like, whoa.
And that's when it kinda hit me.
And so I went back and I
did a bunch of research.
And then it came out that
I had a really severe case
of polycystic ovary syndrome,
which physically changed
my body and made it
difficult for me to produce
the right amount of estrogen.
And I went back to the
doctor because my weight
started to gain again.
'Cause they took me
off all the medication,
they're like, you're fine,
and then I called the doctor,
and I'm like, what's going on?
And he's like, this is something
that you'll always have to deal with.
There is no cure.
And sometimes your medication
is not going to work,
but because I was so
unhealthy and so overweight,
I was just terrified of always
having to be on a drug and,
and never being really
able to maintain my weight
or my emotions or my moods.
And so after that, I kinda was like,
I fell in love with this girl.
And I was just so comfortable with myself.
And, and then I kind of woke
up one day and was like,
man, I think I'm trans.
I was one of those trans
guys was like, you know,
I was kind of like that
jock who's homophobic.
I was super femme, and I
didn't really, you know,
after I got into Yellowstone,
which is the treatment center,
I was just like, why do
girls dress like guys?
And I was just really
trying to, in my mind,
rationalize or try to piece together
what was going on with my body,
in my mind, putting those together.
And then I just let all those,
I was just like, forget it.
And I just, it, it was
really kinda like I woke up
one day and I was like, I was trans.
I knew all along, clearly, the
signs were there, you know?
And when I look back, I'm like,
wow, you know, I was trans.
But I really literally woke up one day
and told my girlfriend
that I thought I was trans.
And that was it.
Before I transitioned, I was like, well,
just everyone call me Jim.
And I was like, Jim's kinda
a white boy's name, you know?
And I was like, I don't know,
And my friend was like,
let's, you know, Jay Bird.
And I was like, okay,
you can just call me Jay.
And so then Jay kind of stuck.
And I thought Jay was kind
of unisex because if I, my,
my ID hadn't been changed and
I hadn't started hormones.
And I was, I did have
kind of feminine features.
So it was a unisex name that I could use
and people wouldn't be like, James,
and you're like, you know?
So I that's what I did.
I did keep my middle name close
to my original middle name,
which was Nicole, so now it's Nicholas,
because I didn't want
my parents to, you know,
I wanted to keep something.
'Cause I think that they, that parents
get so attached to the name, you know?
'Cause children, it's special
and I had a unique name,
sort of, it's kind of popular
now, but Christmas this year,
my name James was on my packages.
They wrote on the calendar
when I was coming home, Jay,
you know what I'm saying?
So they know that's what, where it's at,
and when I'm in public, they really try.
'Cause now people are starting
to look at them crazy,
they're like Katie, you know, come here.
And they're like, what?
So I mean, they're really,
my dad is really good.
My dad has taken it the best.
He put my ass in
construction and it's like,
you're gonna learn a trade, and
if you're going to be a man,
you know, he helped, you know,
he buys me clothes that fit.
And because really, I don't
know how to dress myself.
I mean, I can, I'm starting
to get to the point
where I'm working a 9 to 5
job and I need to wear clothes
that are kind of casual,
but you know, work casual.
And so he really helps me out with that.
Haircuts, you know, telling
me how to cut my hair
so I don't look like a little boy,
'cause I do look young
and just things like that.
So my dad's been really,
really good about,
he's kind of stereotypical.
Like I said, you put me in construction,
you need to learn how to
paint some drywall, you know,
and saw this plank of wood.
But that's what he knows.
And that's great because
I think that there's a lot
of bio men who don't have fathers either.
And I was just blessed to
be able to have a father.
My mom, however, I'm her little
girl and I'm the youngest.
So it's immensely hard.
Like my sister, she prides herself
on having a little sister and my mom
was like my baby, my little baby girl.
And that's what she calls
me and I don't press it.
I'm not a person who
really cares about that.
I just want my parents to love me.
They didn't kick me
out, they're supportive,
and that's all I could
ask for really, you know,
and they don't sweep it under
the rug now like they used to.
They're really coming around,
especially since I'm physically changing.
My dad looked at me one day and he's like,
wow, you're, you're
really looking different.
And so I think tangibly,
when they, when they saw it,
then they were more accepting of the fact
that this is what it was, you know?
I'm still psychologically
going through puberty,
even though I'm grown.
I'm 22 and I'm grown,
I mean, right? (laughs)
No, but I'm I'm older,
you know what I'm saying?
And it's so weird that I'm
like, I wanna look like 50 Cent,
you know, or just, you know,
my physical, you know, image.
I don't care to be a gangster.
I don't really do that.
I don't care to be, which is a lot
of the media portrayal of
black man is that they're hard.
And I don't care anything about that.
'Cause I'm a poet, you know?
So when you go into the poetry scene,
you've got these like cool black dudes
who are just like chill, it's whatever.
So I'm not really concerned
with that so much.
I think it's just physically,
I'm just like, I wanna
be, yeah. I wanna look
kind of like that because
I think I'm still early.
I've only been on testosterone for a year,
so I'm still early in like
my physical transformation.
So I'm like, oh, I kinda want
to have a body like that.
Or I want my voice to be like that.
I think that other people expect me
to be what the media portrays of black men
and that's difficult.
But I struggled with that
in my cheese mode crap all the time.
And I still struggle with it in a sense
that now I question my
own manner to my own,
not to project it so much outwardly,
but I wanna feel it inside.
I don't want to wear this sign of my head
that I'm trans 'cause I'm a man.
Now I don't, I just
want to be with a woman.
And ironically, when I'm down South,
a lot of my female coworkers know,
and they're like, all right, cool.
You know, it doesn't dawn, it's just,
they don't care at all,
and so it's just like...
Weird.
It's so weird.
And up here, they care a little bit more.
I think they care little bit
more, just in my observation,
but down there, they're
just like, that is so sexy,
because here's the thing,
is that it's so patriarchal down there.
It's like women have to
wait on men, hand and foot.
And so here's this man coming
in with this feminine side,
you know, this femininity that is weird,
but still has this kind of
macho machismo thing going on,
but it's not overbearing where it's like,
they're in this form of servitude, almost.
They call it something else there,
what is it, chivalry or whatever.
Which I think is crap.
Will you hold my purse?
It's heavy.
But I think that they like the simple,
the fact that I can be, I hate that both,
but I possess kind of two halves,
because I'm understanding
their feminine experience,
but also able to be a
man, you know, be a man.
(upbeat music)
- Early on in my life,
I think when I was young adult,
it was before I got sober.
I had hitchhiked to Texas and
was being just, you know, bad.
And I met these drag queens
who were taking hormones
and I had this fantasy that someday
I would take hormones and be a man.
I had no idea that it was
possible for one thing,
but that was my fantasy.
And when I met the first couple of guys
in the Bay Area that were transitioning,
it was the first time that I realized
that it could be something
other than a fantasy.
And it was hard.
I mean, 'cause I think
more than anything else,
I was scared to tell my mom, you know,
and I was afraid to face her disapproval.
And I think for a period of time,
I did nothing because I was
afraid of her disapproval.
And then I realized at a certain point
that I was waiting for her to die,
so I could actually live my
life, and that really felt
horrible and morbid to me,
and I decided to move forward,
I took my first shot on my birthday,
and I was so grateful that
my period stopped right away.
That that alone was worth
taking that first shot.
'Cause man feeling like a guy
and having a period just sucks.
It just is such a bad experience
psychologically and emotionally.
And then, you know, I went through
that kind of Peter Brady moment
when my voice was changing
and that was really weird, and
then like hair growth hurts.
I didn't, nobody, I called my brother.
And I said, "Dude, why didn't you tell me
"that this was gonna like hurt,
"and I was going to get
these bumps and be itchy?"
And he said, "Oh, I
figured you'd find out."
I mean, he just, he's a joker.
We get along really well.
But so I mean, that was,
it was interesting to watch
my body change and watch my,
listen to my voice change
and things like that.
And I think in my relationship
there was some difficulty
because neither my wife nor I,
and she wasn't my wife, then,
she was my fiancee then,
we weren't sure that she
would still be attracted to me
the more that I masculinized,
and so that was just really
kind of a wait and see thing,
which was scary, but we had
integrity with each other
about it and it's all worked out well,
but you know, it was, I think
a lot of relationships end
not because there isn't love there,
but for people who are lesbian identified,
even if they're attracted
to butch lesbians,
there's something about being with a man
that is just not
compelling to them at all.
And so you have to honor
that and respect that,
but I got lucky.
I mean, that's all I
can say is I got lucky,
but it's been interesting.
Not because of the transition.
I think in her family,
the idea that she would be
with someone who's African-American
is just abhorrent to them.
She's a mixed race woman,
European-American, and Peruvian.
And I think there's, there's
a certain amount of bigotry
in both sides of her
family line and the notion
that is true often in the black community
and other communities of color,
that you should marry white
to kind of better the race
and preferably someone
of the opposite sex,
so that she brought home
this black trans man
was just not a fun experience.
And her ex, in a fit of pique,
actually emailed her parents
and told them that I was trans.
So I didn't really get
to come out to them.
They already knew.
So there was all this buzz
about it, that was me,
I was it, this thing that she was seeing
and in our relationship, I think
because of that experience,
we were forced to kind
of stand together more
and she's just been, just,
probably the greatest gift of my life.
I mean, she's been,
she's pushed me at times
when I needed to be
pushed and has needled me
and pushed me to be a better
person and a stronger person.
And she's been incredibly supportive.
And for her, it's been very
hard because as as a femme woman
and as a mixed race woman,
she's had a hard time
with her own visibility.
So as a mixed race woman, who's very pale,
she's often mistaken for white.
As a femme woman, the only
way she was kind of identified
as a femme lesbian was
with her butch on her arm.
And so now she's with
this black man in this,
what looks to be straight
married relationship.
And it just, I've been
very thoughtful about her,
the visibility that she's
lost by being with me,
and we've had a lot of discussion about it
and she's been really great.
And so I don't, she has
my permission to out me
wherever she wants to and
wherever it feels comfortable
for her, so that she can
maintain her own integrity.
My wife and I do GLBT diversity trainings
for different organizations,
and it's really kinda fun
because we do a three day training.
The first day is really about,
kind of stereotypes and labels.
And we go through all these
different ways in which people
identify people in the
LGBTQQI communities.
And we spend a lot of
time talking about that,
about people's perceptions,
people's difficulty
trying to intersect the work
that they're trying to do
in human services or in business
and their own kind of maybe spiritual
or religious positions
on what it means to be
in a same sex involvement.
And we just kinda let that
flesh itself out a bit.
The second day, we come out.
So what we look like is
we look like, perhaps,
a married couple of
advocates and activists,
and then my wife comes out
as being lesbian identified,
and I come out as being a trans man,
and we spend time answering a
bunch of questions about that
and talking about the
processes of transition,
because that's what people
are very interested in.
When I do come out to folks,
I think they're surprised.
I haven't had anybody respond negatively,
but I think they're more kind of surprised
and a little bit in shock, excuse me.
And they don't, if they
feel negatively about it,
they haven't bothered to tell me.
It's been, you know, I mean, I think
in the, in the butch lesbian
community, there was a lot of,
I think that was the, the, my
friends who identify as butch
probably gave me the hardest
time about transition.
And I think going from
being kind of an elder
in that community to being a
guy was very hard for folks,
you know, and I also think that,
you know, you go from being
an ally and a strength
and someone that people can
turn to in that community
to being, you know, the
face of their perpetrator
and their oppressor.
And so, I understand
some of that difficulty.
It was hard, it was hurtful,
but I also understand it.
And I took what I call
my, my farewell tour
the year before I transitioned.
And I spent a year really going to all
the women's only spaces
that I would never be able
to visit again, and to just
say, thank you, and to be,
to express gratitude for the nurturing
that came out of the lesbian community,
that allowed me to be
kind of true to myself.
And I miss it sometimes.
I mean, even now, if we go out to a bar,
a lesbian bar or something,
I just feel so weird.
I mean, 'cause all, I'm
looking at these, like I said,
I don't really see myself
very differently, really.
And so I'm looking at folks
and going, "Hey, what's up?"
And they're looking at me like,
what is this guy doing here?
You know, what does he want?
And I realized that I've
traded the opportunity
to be a part of this community
for whatever male privilege
it is I have out in the world
and I wouldn't untrade it,
but it's sometimes difficult
and sometimes uncomfortable.
I'm not sure that it's
affected my masculinity now
as much as it did earlier
in my life as a butch,
and earlier on in transition
because there's that feeling of feeling
like I had to overcompensate
because I was female bodied
and that was more true as a butch.
I think, you know, I couldn't,
I had to be harder than hard
and tougher than tough and I wouldn't cry,
and you know, all that stuff that,
I had to do all those things
because I wasn't a man.
And I think in transition, I realized
I don't have to do anything.
I can be whatever kind of man I wanna be
because now I'm a man,
you know, now it fits.
And I don't think I realized
that I was overcompensating at the time.
I think I was trying to insulate myself
against not being male enough.
I don't know, I really don't think
it was on a conscious level,
but there was something
like a sigh of relief
that happened when I,
when I became integrated,
my insides and my outsides.
And I realized that I can be soft,
and I can be goofy and I can, you know,
I can do whatever I wanna
do because this is who I am.
I don't have to prove anything to anybody.
So the one thing that really
I think is most telling
is that I'm now beginning a relationship
with my body after so
many years of pretending
that it wasn't there.
And so I didn't, I wouldn't
work out, I wouldn't eat right.
I wouldn't take care of my
body because I hated my body.
I didn't want it, you know?
I wanted it to go away
and now I'm kinda working
my way back from that of going, okay,
I've got the body I want now.
Let's see if we can't give it
a little love and attention,
but I think more than anything
else, the greatest impact
was really a divorce
from my physical self.
Like from all those years, even sexually,
I was not willing to be
attached to my physical body.
I'm fortunate enough to
be associated with folks
that are earlier in their transition.
And I encourage them to
take a farewell tour,
you know, take that year and,
and to integrate who you were
with who you're becoming,
because it's all you.
You don't have to flush
away that part of it,
that's part of what will make
you the man that you are.
And I would also say that
it's been important for me
to recognize that my spiritual transition
needed to precede my physical transition,
that the physical transition
without the spiritual
is not fulfilling and is kind of,
perhaps leaning towards
problems down the road
in terms of self acceptance
and acceptance in the world.
And I would say again, give the people
that you are causing
to transition with you
at least as much time
as it took you to find self-acceptance.
Don't be impatient with your
parents and your siblings
and all those folks
'cause they don't get it.
It's not theirs to get, you know?
I mean, we're in a position
when we transition,
we force people to transition with us.
Our loved ones have no choice.
They can either do it gracefully or not,
but we're moving on and
they have to kind of
get dragged along with us.
And so, sometimes that feels
exactly like what's happening to them.
They're getting dragged
along like a hostage.
And we have to try to make room for them
to wrestle with their own stuff.
And in the ways in which
I've found the most loving
to do that is to just be
present and to be whole,
and to be pleased with who I am
and to not be argumentative or defensive,
but to say, "I completely understand
"how you don't understand this.
"I wasn't fortunate enough to be born
"in the body that fit me.
"But if I had, maybe I
wouldn't understand it either,"
you know, give them
room to not understand.
So that's really, and live,
you know, live and love boldly.
That's what I would say, you know?
Find someone that loves
you for who you are,
all of who you are and
don't allow yourself
to be disrespected.
Even if it gets lonely, sometimes,
waiting for someone that can
respect you, it's worth it.
(upbeat music)
- When I was in Vegas, I grew up.
I mean, really I grew up
spiritually, mentally,
emotionally, and everything.
I didn't see my mom and my family,
and those, in some years and every time
they would send me pictures,
I was noticing my family
was getting older.
You know, and I'm like, wow.
You know, there's some nephews and nieces
that I haven't seen.
And my mom was getting older.
I was getting older and I was, you know,
just ready to retire,
basically just start over.
And so, because I haven't seen my family,
and at that time, too, in 2002,
I realized that, you know, my, who I was,
and that's when I first started
transitioning, actually,
2002, and I said, if I wanna transition,
I wanna do it in, I wanna
go back home and do it.
You know, I wanna go somewhere where,
I feel safe, I would just feel safe,
instead of transitioning out
there without any support.
And not saying my family
was supportive, but just,
you know, I don't know,
just support, you know.
Like if anything happened
to me in an operation
or something, you know, I'll
be there with my family,
just something like that.
But before I was able to
come here, I, you know,
I had to write the letters.
I had to tell them, you know,
that I'm about to transition.
So I'm just, because they
haven't seen me in years,
I just don't want to just go out there,
and just say, "Hey," 'cause I was always,
I still always kind of kept in contact
with my family all the time,
talk to my mom all the time.
So I was calling them up and like,
"Yeah, I'm changing my name."
And they was like, yeah.
'Cause you know, I was the type of person,
I was the quote-unquote "gypsy."
So whatever, any changes I
did, it was like, oh, okay.
And then they made it okay
for me to be who I was.
And as growing up as a child,
you want your family to say,
okay, 'cause it was never about,
it was never about the friends
and the people outside.
It was always about my family,
you know, what they think.
And if they didn't, I would
say who gives a fuck anyway,
I'm not supposed to quit,
but just as long as,
if I got that as something,
if I didn't, it was like,
oh, well, I'm gonna still
do what I want to do anyway.
But just to, I guess, just
to make it okay for me
to not have to worry, that
was a little, one less thing
I had to worry about is like
struggling with my family,
with who I was, you know?
And that was a blessing.
My aunts and uncles and
cousins, they like secondary,
you know, so, but they okay with it.
What they say, they
said, "Hey, little cuz,"
they just called me "little cuz."
they don't even go to the name.
My cousin's like, "Hey, little cuz,"
we were laughing, like
whatever your name is,
just you my cousin, so
that's how we relate.
But the hardest one, the emotional,
was my baby sister.
That's my sister.
That was my heart.
That was not was, but she still is.
She could not get it.
She, she wasn't gonna get it.
She told me I'm not gonna,
she's the only one verbally expressed it.
You know, my other, they was just like,
they did ask, but my sis
said, "I don't understand it.
"I don't like it, I don't get it."
And we even went through the
point where she even cried,
you know, I ain't know black
people would do that, either.
But because of her background, she was,
she was into more church
and she was into her,
she was into a little bit
experience of life, too,
to where she just, (sighing)
because, and the reason being that I knew,
and I knew she was gonna take the hardest,
because we were the closest sibling.
Even though I was close
to my other siblings,
but we were more the closest
as far as sharing our feelings
and what we're gonna be when we grow up.
I know one day, when I first
moved back here, like I said,
I went to each and I mean,
literally each and every
one of my family homes that I'd thought,
that I wanted to let know.
And when I, when I told
my niece and nephew,
which she did not like that, she said,
"Why didn't you tell them that?
"I don't want them to call you uncle.
"I don't want them to do that."
And I said, "Well, if we're
gonna hang out together
"and when I'm going to
come over your house,
"I'm not going to allow them
to call me anything else."
I said, "You decide how
you, how you want them
"to approach me, but
I'm not gonna allow them
"to call me auntie," and my
nephew, he's like 16, 17 now.
So he didn't, he don't say anything.
He just like, you know,
if he wants something,
he just asks, he doesn't call
me by any name or whatever.
This is my sister.
Like, since I've been
out of here, holidays,
we, we spend together,
we talk on the phone,
and I go over to her house for holidays
and we do still play the games.
We still play Monopoly and laugh 'til 2:00
in the morning now today.
And, you know, and play cards or whatever,
you know, gin rummy,
she likes to play that.
You know, we still do those things.
So that part didn't go away.
And I think the
misconception, just for people
and family is that I'm
just gonna just be a total
whatever the stereotype of a guy is.
I'm just going to be this asshole,
or I'm gonna be this aggressive person.
And for me, that didn't never change.
And my mom, she never treated me,
well, she never forced me,
you know, I hear a lot of stories where,
you know, they were
forced to wear dresses,
and forced to be girly.
My mom, she was, it's like, you know,
they say your mom knew,
you know, and just looking,
I know my mom knew I was different.
And so she allowed me to be different,
you know, 'cause I always
spoke my mind and I say, no,
I don't wanna, I say
yes, this is what I want.
And so my mom allowed me to be who I was
without, you know, being
disrespectful to adults.
'Cause back then adults,
they'd get in your butt
back then, you know?
And when I knew, just growing up
that my mom allowed me to say yes or no,
or I don't want this,
or I don't like this,
or I wanna go here, it helped me in life,
that I don't have to be a
yes person all the time.
Well, depending on the
type of relationship type,
with the type of women I
was in, I was always, a yes,
you know, yes, yes,
honey, yes, this and that.
That that came later in life.
My mom didn't tell me it
wasn't gonna be like that.
Man, she didn't tell me about that part,
but my brothers did, you're
talking about growing up.
One of my biggest mentor was my brother.
He passed away, in '03,
but he taught me the,
he taught me the bad side of growing up.
He taught me, you know, what women like,
what women, what they
expect and how to treat them
and what to do, when they say this
and it wasn't the right thing to do,
but it worked, it worked
up until, you know,
I've met as I get older, I met a woman
that knew, you know, it's
like, she knew my brother.
She knew guys like my brother.
She was like, that's now how it works.
My mom taught me this, you know?
And I always say, once I met my match,
the last relationship I was in,
I met my match and it was
like, I had to either change
or I have to start dating younger girls
that didn't know any different.
So, but I always dated, women,
like a mixture of my
mom and my two sisters.
Because my sisters, they're beautiful,
and I love my sisters and my mom.
So always, mix them up, I take
out this part of my mother,
this part of my sister and
this part of my baby sister,
and those type of women I dated.
It's like, like I was saying,
I don't know about other
guys, but I was wondering
who was going to like me,
who's going to be attracted
to trans guy, you know?
'Cause I know I love all women,
but I didn't know what women do I date?
So I had to test it,
I had to try to date the straight women,
and then you have to reveal,
or date a bisexual women, that was okay.
Lesbian, they just cut the door again.
But I keep saying, but the bi women,
I found out that,
for me, my personal experience,
that bisexual women are more
attracted to feminine women.
That's just my experience of all,
the dating I've done, and
I was like dating a lot,
not sleeping with people, dating.
I wanna clear that up.
I was dating, I mean a
lot, like every weekend
or every month, I'll
date someone, and then,
but it was more so I was
asking them questions
of how they feel about trans guys.
I call it a date, they'd call it a date.
But me mainly, I was trying
to figure out who likes me?
What are, what type of women
are attracted to trans guys?
And I found, a handful
that knew trans guys
and that was attracted to trans guys.
But because I'm human and I like people
to be attracted to me,
a whole bowl full of guys
was more attracted to me.
But in the beginning,
not knowing who liked me
or if I was going to ever date again,
'cause that was a thing.
I didn't think about it before.
But once I transitioned,
it was like, you know,
so I would date a lot of men, you know?
I would still, always date women,
but I was dating a lot
of men and you know,
and they would feed your
ego and they was, you know,
they attracted to trans guys.
There's a lot of, you know,
my experience just me,
there's a lot of guys and
we're talking bisexual guys,
straight guys that attracted to trans men
and it blew my mind.
So that's that in a nutshell.
But right now, you know, I haven't been
in a committed relationship in six years
and that's because of my school
is number one in my life.
You know, I've had relationships,
I'd shacked up, lived up and you know,
I'm not, so my my school
is number one in my life.
But as far as the dating,
nah, I came to realize,
that, you know, I still wait
for my wife and my kids,
you know, but that experience of who I am,
who likes me, what I am, you know,
'cause I could never see myself
settling down with a guy, I never could,
but then I did get the idea,
I was like, well maybe.
And then it was like,
no, I'm just doing that
because I want that attraction,
and I know the difference
between, you know, just the attraction,
for the feeling wanted or
needed or you know, love.
I know the difference today,
I can say, of fond feelings.
(claps) That sums that up in a nutshell.
Next question. (laughs)
(upbeat music)
- Hi, Carl Madgett from Chicago, Illinois.
Be who you are and love who you are.
(upbeat music)
- My name is Ethan Young.
I'm 49 years old.
I live in Toledo, Ohio.
And if the world was all tattooed,
it'd be a much better place.
(upbeat music)
- Kylar Broadus, Columbia,
Missouri, world peace.
(upbeat music)
- James Welch, Evanston, Illinois.
Be honest.
(upbeat music)
- My name is Nicholas Ishmael Rashad,
born and raised South Suburb of Chicago.
And what I truly believe,
if everyone believe in loving themselves,
is that that's what you're
gonna get in return,
is what you put out there is what you get.
(upbeat music)
- My name is Louis Mitchell and I live
in Springfield, Massachusetts.
Don't ever believe that
God doesn't love you,
and that you're unlovable.